<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<NAF version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <nafHeader>
    <fileDesc author="UWA" creationtime="2025-01-14" filename="engineering-change-10-years-of-championing-diversity-in-stem.xml" filetype="HTML" title="Engineering change - 10 years of championing diversity in STEM"/>
    <public publicId="592e71dd-8466-4c9b-af88-0ef230b0fe90" uri="https://www.uwa.edu.au/news/article/2025/january/engineering-change-10-years-of-championing-diversity-in-stem"/>
  </nafHeader>
  <raw>

The University of Western Australia's Girls+ in Engineering program is celebrating a major milestone, marking 10 years of inspiring and empowering the next generation of women+ in STEM. 

The program, launched in 2014 in partnership with Rio Tinto, was Western Australia's first gender-specific STEM outreach initiative. 

Since its inception it has reached over 20,000 students and has become a hugely successful transformative program, for primary and high school students, student ambassadors, industry partners and the wider WA community.

Dean and Head of School at UWA’s School of Engineering, Professor Tim Sercombe, said the School took pride in industry partnerships, and that the GiE outreach program stood as a testament to the power of collaboration.

“Since launching, Girls+ in Engineering has played a pivotal role in increasing female enrolments and enhancing the student experience through initiatives like the Student Ambassador program,” Professor Sercombe said.

“We’re now looking forward to building on this success with our industry partners as we work towards greater inclusion and equality in engineering.”

From its initial partnerships with five metropolitan schools, GiE has expanded to reach 26 WA schools, including regional, remote and low socioeconomic areas across Perth, Pilbara and Great Southern. 

Regional engagement has been a key focus in expanding the reach of GiE, with the program having engaged more than 1,700 high school students in the Pilbara since 2017, and 1,375 high school students in the Great Southern since 2022

UWA Manager Student Equity Katie Douglas said the program’s impact extended beyond numbers, creating lasting change through hands-on workshops, discovery days and mentoring opportunities.

“Since 2014, GiE has delivered 710 workshops across 329 unique school visits and welcomed nearly 6,000 students to campus for Discovery Day events,” Ms Douglas said.

“The program’s impact extends to its Student Ambassador program, which has supported over 350 ambassadors and collected more than 1,800 volunteer hours.

“Its success is evident in its extensive reach and achievements, including finalist positions in prestigious awards including the Western Australia Premier's Science Awards and Australian Finance Review Higher Education Awards.” 

More recently, the Girls in Engineering Student Ambassador Program won a UWA Award for Excellence and Innovation in Learning and Teaching in Diversity, Equity and Inclusion. 

GiE Student Ambassador Georgia Gould described her involvement with the Ambassador Program as one of the highlights of her university experience. 

“Throughout my time with Girls in Engineering, I have had so many opportunities for my own personal development,” Georgia said. 

“I feel empowered, my confidence has grown, I've made countless friend, and I’ve had employment opportunities both within the university and with industry.” 

Industry partnerships have also strengthened over the decade, with Rio Tinto's continued support since the inception of the program and additional backing from Newmont Australia and global technology company SLB. 

“These collaborations have enabled practical experiences for students, including site visits to operations such as Rio Tinto's Marandoo Iron Ore mine and Newmont Australia's Boddington mine.”

Career Practitioner at Albany Senior High School Nina Goodwin said the partnership not only enriched students but had reinforced the relationship between the high school and UWA.

“Particularly by fostering local connections with the UWA Albany Campus, a connection that is invaluable, as it helps our young people understand the study options available to them right in their own backyard, removing barriers to higher education and career development,” she said.

Rio Tinto Senior Advisor Research and Development Iron Ore Hannah Golding said supporting a program that connected high school students with industry through hands-on activities, inspiring role models and immersive campus events was a privilege.

“As someone who has wrestled with self-doubt about my place in the STEM community, I aim to empower students by showing them they can overcome challenges and find confidence through achievement,” Ms Golding said.

“This ongoing commitment to Girls+ in Engineering opens pathways into STEM careers, transforming futures and advancing diversity in engineering.”

Girls in Engineering has dedicated itself to fostering the next generation of innovators, leaders, and changemakers in STEM.  As GiE celebrates its tenth anniversary, the program remains committed to contributing to supporting a more equitable STEM future for WA.  


</raw>
</NAF>