<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<NAF version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <nafHeader>
    <fileDesc author="UWA" creationtime="2024-12-03" filename="state-government-renews-funding-for-road-safety-research.xml" filetype="HTML" title="State Government renews funding for road safety research"/>
    <public publicId="592e71dd-8466-4c9b-af88-0ef230b0fe90" uri="https://www.uwa.edu.au/news/article/2025/january/engineering-change-10-years-of-championing-diversity-in-stem"/>
  </nafHeader>
  <raw>

The University of Western Australia has welcomed today’s State Government’s announcement that it will extend funding for the Western Australian Centre for Road Safety Research for a further five years.

In 2019, UWA successfully tendered for the establishment of the WA Centre for Road Safety Research. The contract awarded was for an initial term of five years with a five-year extension option.

Led by internationally recognised road safety researcher Professor Teresa Senserrick, the centre launched a new hi-tech driving simulator earlier this year, enabling researchers to investigate a range of safety issues with the aim of reducing serious crashes on our roads.

Minister for Road Safety David Michael said under the new funding agreement, the centre would focus on driver behaviour change, including understanding road user behaviours and attitudes, and the cultural factors that might influence risky driving/riding behaviour.

Associate Professor Paul Roberts, Deputy Director of UWA’s Centre for Road Safety Research, said the funding extension would enable researchers to build on current research projects.

“These projects include analysing young drivers’ behaviour and their responses to challenges such as mobile phone distractions, fatigue and the impact of drugs and alcohol,” Associate Professor Roberts said.

“We also have a strong focus on evidence-based approaches to road safety education for all road users, including reach to Aboriginal communities and various forms of transport, including motorcycles, heavy vehicles and eRideables.

“In addition to our driving simulator research, a current focus is on the factors that affect drivers’ speed choice, and the perception of risk associated with speed.

“Speed is a contributing factor in around half of all fatal crashes, so this work is critical to improve safety on the road for the WA community."

</raw>
</NAF>